- Are you ready, kids?
- 孩子们，你们准备好了吗？
kids:
Aye, aye, Captain!
孩子们：
是啊是啊，队长！
- I can't hear you.
- 我听不到你说话。
kids:
Aye, aye, Captain!
孩子们：
是啊是啊，队长！
- ♪ Ohh... ♪
- ♪ 哦...♪
♪ Who lives in a pineapple
under the sea? ♪
♪ 谁住在菠萝里
在海底？ ♪
kids:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
孩子们：
海绵宝宝！
- ♪ Absorbent and yellow
and porous is he ♪
- ♪ 吸水性和黄色
他是多孔的 ♪
kids:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
孩子们：
海绵宝宝！
- ♪ If nautical nonsense
be something you wish ♪
- ♪ 如果航海废话
成为你想要的东西♪
kids:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
孩子们：
海绵宝宝！
- ♪ Then drop on the deck
and flop like a fish ♪
- ♪ 然后落在甲板上
然后像鱼一样扑通扑通♪
kids: SpongeBob SquarePants!
- Ready?
孩子们：海绵宝宝！
- 准备好？
all:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
全部：
海绵宝宝！
SpongeBob SquarePants!
- SpongeBob
- 海绵宝宝
SquarePants!
方裤！
[laughing]
[笑]
[flute plays]
[长笛演奏]
[waves crashing]
[海浪拍打]
[upbeat music]
[欢快的音乐]
♪ ♪
- [snoring]
- [打鼾]
[horn blares]
[喇叭声]
- Good morning, alarm clock.
- 早上好，闹钟。
[horn blares]
[喇叭声]
- Ah.
- 啊。
Whoa!
哇！
Ha!
哈!
Ah.
啊。
Hmm.
唔。
Choices, choices.
选择，选择。
[laughs]
[笑]
Whoa!
哇！
Whoops.
哎呀。
Pants are a little
twisted around.
裤子有点小
扭曲。
Heh.
呵呵。
Ah.
啊。
[trumpet plays]
[喇叭演奏]
Whoa!
哇！
Whoops.
哎呀。
Almost forgot
my lucky tie clip.
差点忘了
我的幸运领带夹。
I'm ready!
我准备好了！
♪ La, la, la, la, la,
la, la, la, la, la, la ♪
♪ 啦，啦，啦，啦，啦，
啦啦啦啦啦啦啦♪
[piano playing]
[钢琴演奏]
Young lady, allow me.
年轻的女士，请允许我。
- Oh, you.
- 哦，你。
[engines droning]
[发动机嗡嗡声]
- Morning, SpongeBob.
- 早上好，海绵宝宝。
- Good morning, Sewer Man.
- 早上好，下水道工。
- There goes one lucky boy.
- 一位幸运的男孩走了。
- See you tomorrow, sweetie.
- 明天见，亲爱的。
- [scatting]
- [分散]
Whoopsie!
哎哟！
- Whoa, whoa.
- 哇哦，哇哦。
- Ah.
- 啊。
Ha-ha.
哈哈。
Good morning, Squidward.
早上好，章鱼哥。
- [grumbles]
- [抱怨]
And why are you
so peppy this morning?
而你为什么是
今天早上这么精神吗？
- Because today
is my lucky day,
- 因为今天
是我的幸运日，
thanks to my lucky tie clip.
感谢我的幸运领带夹。
- Don't you wear that
tie clip every day?
- 你不穿那个吗
每天都用领带夹吗？
- Uh-huh.
- 呃哈。
Every day is my lucky day.
每一天都是我的幸运日。
- [laughs]
- [笑]
- Pfft, luck isn't real.
- 噗，运气不是真的。
It's all in your head.
一切都在你的脑海里。
- Squidward, it's unlucky
not to believe in luck.
- 章鱼哥，真不走运
不要相信运气。
- Hmph.
- 哼。
- Sorry, Mr. Squidward.
- 对不起，章鱼哥先生。
Didn't see you there.
在那儿没看到你。
- [grumbling]
- [抱怨]
- [giggles]
- [咯咯笑]
[giggles]
[咯咯笑]
One Krabby Patty pickle deluxe,
perfectly prepared.
一份豪华蟹肉饼泡菜，
准备充分。
- Hmm.
- 唔。
I'll be the judge of that.
我将对此做出判断。
[murmuring]
[淙淙]
- Hmm.
- 唔。
I want to complain.
我想投诉。
But it's too delectable!
但这也太赏心悦目了吧！
[cheering]
[欢呼]
- How?
- 如何？
How did you accomplish
such perfection?
你是如何完成的
如此完美？
- Guess I'm just lucky.
- 我想我只是幸运而已。
♪ ♪
♪ La, la, la, la ♪
♪ 啦，啦，啦，啦 ♪
Whoa.
哇哦。
Whoa, whoa!
Ah!
哇哦！
啊!
Whoops.
哎呀。
[glass shatters]
[玻璃碎裂]
- [snoring]
- [打鼾]
[horn blares]
[喇叭声]
- Ready to start
another lucky day, Gary?
- 准备开始
又是幸运的一天，加里？
- [meows]
- [喵]
- Whoa!
- 哇！
Whoa.
哇哦。
Hey.
嘿。
Huh?
啊？
Ah!
啊!
Where's my lucky tie clip?
我的幸运领带夹在哪里？
Not here.
不在这里。
No.
不。
Nuh-uh.
呃呃。
[toilet flushes]
[厕所冲水]
[blower droning]
[鼓风机嗡嗡声]
[dishes clattering]
[餐具碰撞声]
No!
不！
My lucky tie clip is missing.
我的幸运领带夹不见了。
[cuckooing]
[布谷鸟]
Oh no.
哦不。
I'm late for work.
我上班迟到了。
I'll search for it later.
稍后我会寻找它。
Wah, nah, ah, whoa!
哇啊啊啊啊啊啊！
[screaming]
[尖叫]
[electricity buzzing]
[电声嗡嗡响]
[laughter]
[笑声]
Whoa!
哇！
- Oh, sorry.
- 哦，抱歉。
I was running late today.
我今天迟到了。
Jeez, what bad luck.
哎呀，运气真差。
- Give me your wallet.
Make it snappy.
- 把你的钱包给我。
让它变得活泼。
- Uh, uh.
- 呃，呃。
- See you tomorrow, sweetie.
- 明天见，亲爱的。
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
[screaming]
- Whoopsie.
[尖叫]
- 哎哟。
- Hot dog.
- 热狗。
Get your hot--
让你热起来——
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
[screaming]
[尖叫]
[gasping]
[喘气]
- What happened to you?
- 你怎么了？
- I lost my lucky tie clip, and
now everything is going wrong.
- 我丢失了我的幸运领带夹，并且
现在一切都出了问题。
- [scoffs]
There's no such thing as luck.
- [嘲笑]
没有所谓的运气。
Your dumb tie clip has
nothing to do with it.
你那愚蠢的领带夹有
与此无关。
- Oh, poor naive Squidward.
-哦，可怜的天真的章鱼哥。
Whoa!
哇！
[groans]
[呻吟]
Oh, spatula cramp.
哦，铲子抽筋了。
Aw.
噢。
[sniffs]
[嗅嗅]
[moans]
[呻吟声]
[screaming]
[尖叫]
[alarm ringing]
[警报响起]
- [grumbles]
- [抱怨]
- Do you have any
recommendations?
- 你有吗
建议？
- Yeah.
- 是的。
Eat somewhere else.
- Hmm.
去别的地方吃。
- 唔。
Excellent advice.
非常好的建议。
Thank you, young man.
谢谢你，年轻人。
- A tip?
- 小费？
Must be my lucky day.
一定是我的幸运日。
Not that I believe
in that nonsense.
不是我相信的
在那废话中。
- [groaning]
- [呻吟]
One Krabby Patty combo.
一份蟹肉饼组合。
- Hmph.
- 哼。
[chomping]
[咀嚼]
Hmm.
唔。
The soda is flat,
the fries are oily,
苏打水是平的，
薯条很油腻，
and the Krabby Patty is bland.
蟹肉饼很平淡。
- B-b-b-bland?
- 平淡平淡？
[groans]
[呻吟]
- What's the matter
with you, boyo?
- 怎么了
和你在一起吗，男孩？
- Aw, I'm bad luck, Mr. Krabs.
- 哦，我运气不好，蟹老板。
Bad luck.
厄运。
- Bad luck?
- 运气不好？
The restaurant
business runs on luck.
餐厅
生意靠运气。
If bad luck sets in,
the Krusty Krab is doomed.
如果运气不好的话
蟹堡王注定要失败。
Everyone out!
大家都出去吧！
Out, out, out, out, out.
出去，出去，出去，出去，出去。
I got to burn some
dried kelp and cleanse
我得烧一些
干海带并洗净
this joint of any bad mojo.
这个关节有任何不好的魔力。
[panicked gasping]
[惊慌地喘气]
- SpongeBob!
Squidward!
- 海绵宝宝！
章鱼哥！
Take the day off.
- Day off?
请一天假。
- 休息日？
No!
不！
- Yes!
- 是的！
- [groaning]
- [呻吟]
I hope my good luck went
to someone who needed it.
我希望我的好运过去了
给需要它的人。
- [laughs]
Huh?
- [笑]
啊？
[awed tone]
[敬畏的语气]
A hair?
一根头发？
Maybe I'm getting
SpongeBob's good luck.
也许我正在得到
海绵宝宝祝你好运。
Ya, ta, ta, ta,
ya, ta, ta, ta.
呀，他，他，他，
呀，他，他，他。
- Hey, Patrick.
- Hey, SpongeBob!
- 嘿，帕特里克。
- 嘿，海绵宝宝！
You OK?
你还好吗？
- I lost my lucky tie clip.
- 我丢失了我的幸运领带夹。
I am now the unluckiest
person alive.
我现在是最不幸的一个
人还活着。
Can I have a hug?
我可以拥抱一下吗？
- No, thank you.
- 不，谢谢。
I wouldn't touch you
with a 10-foot pole.
我不会碰你
用一根 10 英尺长的杆子。
I don't want your bad luck
to rub off on me.
我不想让你运气不好
来影响我。
- Oh, what am I going to do?
- 哦，我该怎么办？
- Hmm.
- 唔。
Why don't you find
a new lucky charm?
你为什么不找
新的幸运符？
- Great idea.
- 好主意。
Thanks, Patrick.
谢谢，帕特里克。
[humming]
[嗡嗡声]
- I don't know what
I'd do without you,
- 我不知道什么
没有你我也行
my lucky 11-foot pole.
我幸运的 11 英尺长的杆子。
[kissing]
[接吻]
- Lucky, lucky, lucky, lucky.
- 幸运，幸运，幸运，幸运。
Oh, a four-leaf kelp.
哦，四叶海带。
They're really lucky.
他们真的很幸运。
- [screams]
A new freeway?
- [尖叫]
一条新的高速公路？
That's not lucky.
这并不幸运。
Ow, ow.
噢，噢。
A sea bunny's foot.
海兔的脚。
They're extra lucky.
他们格外幸运。
- [growls]
- [咆哮]
- Unless it's still
attached to the sea bunny.
- 除非它还在
附着在海兔身上。
[screaming]
[尖叫]
Sorry.
对不起。
[thunder crashing]
[雷霆轰鸣]
[groans]
[呻吟]
[chatter]
[喋喋不休]
- [groaning]
- [呻吟]
Huh?
啊？
[upbeat music]
[欢快的音乐]
Squidward?
章鱼哥？
[cheering]
[欢呼]
- Some people have all the
luck, SpongeBob, just not you.
- 有些人拥有所有
海绵宝宝，运气好，只是不是你。
[laughter]
[笑声]
- [crying]
- [哭泣]
Huh?
啊？
My tie clip?
我的领带夹？
I had it with me all day?
我整天都带着它吗？
Huh, it was just
like Squidward said.
呵呵，本来就是
正如章鱼哥所说。
Hey, Squidward, you were right.
嘿，章鱼哥，你是对的。
Luck was all just in my head.
运气只在我的脑海里。
I don't need this solid
gold lucky tie clip.
我不需要这个固体
金色幸运领带夹。
[whistles]
[口哨声]
But it never hurts
to be on the safe side.
但它永远不会痛
为了安全起见。
[laughter]
[笑声]
♪
Hey, Squidward,
my good luck is back.
嘿，章鱼哥，
我的好运又回来了。
Back in my head.
回到我的脑海里。
- Hold on.
- 坚持，稍等。
If SpongeBob's luck
is back, then--
如果海绵宝宝运气好的话
回来了，那么——
[playing discordantly]
[演奏不和谐]
[booing, jeering]
[嘘声、嘲笑声]
Oh, no.
哦，不。
Just my luck.
只是我的运气。
[upbeat music]
[欢快的音乐]
♪ ♪
[laughter]
[笑声]
- Ooh, you got him, Patrick.
- 哦，你抓住了他，帕特里克。
- You're mine now, jelly!
- 你现在是我的了，果冻！
[grunts]
[咕哝]
[snoring]
[打鼾]
[gasping]
[喘气]
Huh?
啊？
How long was I out?
我出去多久了？
- About a week.
- 大约一周。
- Whoo, a new record!
- 哇，新纪录！
[laugh]
[笑]
Yeah, it's all
in the old wrist.
是啊，就这样了
在老手腕上。
[snoring]
[打鼾]
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
Ah, nothing like a day
of napping to tucker you out.
啊，没有什么比一天
打盹让你精疲力尽。
Good night, Mr. Lamp.
晚安，灯先生。
Huh, not sleeping yet.
呵呵，还没睡呢。
Oh, maybe if I lay this way.
哦，也许如果我这样躺着的话。
[groaning]
[呻吟]
I guess I'll just sit up
and wait to get sleepy.
我想我会坐起来
并等待困倦。
Hmph.
哼。
[groans]
[呻吟]
I've been waiting
to sleep all day!
我一直在等待
睡一整天！
Oh, it's already
half past a freckle.
哦，已经是了
雀斑过去了一半。
Guess I'll see what
SpongeBob's doing.
我猜我会看到什么
海绵宝宝在做。
- [snoring]
- [打鼾]
- Want to hang out?
- 想出去玩吗？
- Oh, Patrick, it's you.
- 哦，帕特里克，是你。
What are you doing
here so late?
你在做什么
这么晚了？
- I can't sleep.
- 我睡不着。
Let's do stuff!
我们来做事吧！
- Um, OK, sure, but I have
to be up in four hours.
- 嗯，好吧，当然，但我有
四小时后起床。
- Perfect!
- 完美的！
- Whoa!
- 哇！
[bright music]
[明亮的音乐]
- [grunting]
- [咕哝]
I can't believe
you're beating me!
我不敢相信
你在打我！
Uh.
呃。
You win again?
你又赢了？
All right.
好的。
Best 200 out of 300.
300 名中最好的 200 名。
- [mumbling]
- [咕哝]
- First one to dig
to rock bottom wins.
- 第一个挖的
到最低点获胜。
Dum, dum, dum, dum, dum, dum.
达姆，达姆，达姆，达姆，达姆，达姆。
[babbling]
[胡说]
- [sighs]
- [叹气]
Patrick, this is
really fun and all,
帕特里克，这是
真的很有趣，
but I need to get to bed.
但我需要去睡觉了。
- But I still can't sleep.
- 但我还是睡不着。
- Patrick, you've got to get
some sleep and fast, or else
- 帕特里克，你必须得到
一些睡眠和禁食，否则
you could start seeing things.
你可以开始看到事物。
- Wait.
- 等待。
I'm seeing things now.
我现在看到了一些事情。
House.
Ground.
房子。
地面。
Sky!
天空！
Make it stop, SpongeBob!
让它停止吧，海绵宝宝！
Make it stop.
让它停止。
- Don't worry, pal.
-别担心，朋友。
I'll help you get to--
我会帮助你到达——
[snoring]
[打鼾]
- Hey, that's my sleep.
- 嘿，这就是我的睡眠。
- Huh?
- 啊？
[groans]
Sleep.
[呻吟]
睡觉吧。
All you need is a good
tucking in and some warm milk.
你所需要的只是一个好的
吃点热牛奶。
And some chamomile tea.
还有一些甘菊茶。
[pop]
[流行音乐]
And my favorite lullaby.
还有我最喜欢的摇篮曲。
[soft music]
[轻音乐]
♪ ♪
- [snoring]
- [打鼾]
- SpongeBob,
I still can't sleep.
- 海绵宝宝，
我还是睡不着。
Huh?
啊？
Oh, looks like I'll have to
do this the old-fashioned way.
哦，看来我得
用老式的方法来做。
Oh, I'm still awake.
哦，我还醒着。
Still awake.
还醒着。
[grunts]
[咕哝]
I think it's working.
我认为它正在发挥作用。
No.
不。
Ugh.
啊。
I didn't want to do this,
but I'm down to my last resort.
我本来不想这样做
但我已经采取了最后的手段。
- Hi, Squidward.
- 嗨，章鱼哥。
- Patrick, what could
you possibly want
- 帕特里克，什么可以
你可能想要
at this hour of the night?
深夜这个时候？
- [sighs]
- [叹气]
I need to hear your life story.
我需要听听你的人生故事。
- Just as I thought,
an idiotic--
——正如我所想的那样，
一个白痴——
what?
什么？
You need to hear my life story?
你需要听听我的人生故事吗？
- Yep.
- 是的。
- Well, it's such short notice.
- 好吧，通知这么短。
I don't have anything prepared,
我什么都没有准备
except this rough manuscript.
除了这份粗糙的手稿。
I call it "Tentacles:
Eight Legs, Eight Lives."
我称之为“触手：
八条腿，八条命。”
- But you only have four legs.
- 但你只有四条腿。
- And two arms.
- 还有两只手臂。
- Oh, yeah.
- 哦，是的。
Yeah, that makes eight.
是的，那就是八个。
- [clears throat]
Chapter 1.
- [清喉咙]
第一章。
"In my youth,
my brilliance was evident.
“在我的青春里，
我的才华是显而易见的。
"Instead of wasting my time
making friends, I made art.
“与其浪费我的时间
交朋友，我创造艺术。
"I recall making a rather
sophisticated tentacle painting
“我记得做了一个相当
精致的触手画
that even my teacher--"
就连我的老师——”
- Wait a minute.
- 等一下。
I'm not getting sleepy.
我不困了。
I'm just getting bored.
我只是觉得无聊了。
- "--and perplexity
as I was bequeathed
——”——以及困惑
正如我被遗赠的那样
an award for my achievements."
对我的成就的奖励。”
- Huh.
- 嗯。
Well, at least
my pipe works for him.
嗯，至少
我的烟斗为他工作。
If I'm not sleepy,
如果我不困的话
I'll just have
to tire myself out.
我只要
让自己疲惫不堪。
Oh, a hot dog!
哦，热狗！
Give me!
给我！
[laughing]
[笑]
- [grunting]
- [咕哝]
Give me.
给我。
[grunting]
[咕噜声]
Ah!
啊!
I've got you now,
you little old man.
我现在已经拥有你了
你这个小老头。
- You want to see
a picture of my grandkids?
- 你想看
我孙子的照片？
- [laughing]
- [笑]
- Uh, hi, Patrick.
- 呃，嗨，帕特里克。
Still not sleeping, huh?
还没睡吧？
- How can you tell?
- 你怎么知道？
- Just a hunch.
[laughs]
- 只是一种预感。
[笑]
Looks like you need
a visit from the Sandman.
看起来你需要
睡魔来访。
He'd blow a little
sand in your eyes,
他会吹一点
眼睛里进了沙子，
and you'd be out like a light.
你就会像一盏灯一样消失。
- A Sandman.
[laughs]
- 沙人。
[笑]
Eyes, out like a light!
眼睛，像光一样！
[maniacal laughter]
[疯狂的笑声]
- OK.
See you later.
- 好的。
稍后见。
- [laughing]
- [笑]
Me make Sandman.
我制作桑德曼。
[laughter]
[笑声]
[spooky music]
[诡异的音乐]
OK, Mr. Sandman.
好的，桑德曼先生。
Now blow sand in my eyes
and put me to sleep.
现在把沙子吹进我的眼睛里
并让我入睡。
What's wrong?
怎么了？
You need more sand?
你需要更多的沙子吗？
- [laughing]
- [笑]
- Huh?
- 啊？
Gah!
嘎！
- [laughing]
- [笑]
- Get back here!
- 回到这里！
- Ooh, you'll have
to catch me first.
- 哦，你会有
先抓住我。
- [yelling]
- [大喊]
- Whee!
- 呼！
[car alarm blaring]
[汽车警报器响]
- Hey, cool, a raving lunatic.
- 嘿，酷，一个疯狂的疯子。
- I'll chase you to the ends
of the ocean, Sandman!
- 我会追你到底
海洋的沙人！
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
Gah!
嘎！
- [giggling]
- [咯咯笑]
- Finally.
- 最后。
Oh, oh, that's it.
哦，哦，就是这样。
Keep it coming.
继续吧。
Oh, where are you going?
哦，你要去哪里？
- [laughing]
- [笑]
- I'm not sleepy yet!
- 我还没睡！
- Meow!
- 喵！
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
- Come on.
More!
- 快点。
更多的！
Where are you going?
你要去哪里？
Better.
But I need more!
更好的。
但我需要更多！
- Ooh-hoo!
- 哦呼！
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
- [laughing]
- [笑]
[blows raspberry]
[吹覆盆子]
- Sandman, your stupid
sleep sand doesn't work!
- 桑德曼，你这个傻瓜
睡沙没用！
- Patrick, stop!
- 帕特里克，停下来！
That's no Sandman.
那不是桑德曼。
That's Squidward.
那是章鱼哥。
- Ay, ay.
- 哎呀。
[groaning]
[呻吟]
- Oops.
- 哎呀。
- [groaning]
- [呻吟]
Hmph.
哼。
Another misadventure
for my memoir.
又是一次不幸的遭遇
为了我的回忆录。
- It's no use, SpongeBob.
- 这没有用，海绵宝宝。
All the Sandman's sand
couldn't make me sleepy.
所有沙人的沙子
无法让我昏昏欲睡。
I guess I'll just be awake
for the rest of my life.
我想我会醒来
我的余生。
- Oh, aha.
- 哦，啊哈。
If you're going
to be awake forever,
如果你要去的话
永远保持清醒，
then you might as well
put that to good use.
那么你也可以
充分利用它。
- [laughs]
- [笑]
SpongeBob, you were right.
海绵宝宝，你是对的。
My "awakeyness"
makes me the perfect
我的“清醒”
让我变得完美
all-night long-haul trucker.
通宵长途卡车司机。
[horn honks]
[喇叭鸣响]
- 10-4, good buddy.
- 10-4，好哥们。
- All right,
keep your rubber side down
- 好吧，
将橡胶面朝下
and the bugs off your glass.
以及玻璃上的虫子。
I'll catch you on the flip.
我会立刻抓住你。
[snoring]
[打鼾]
[beeping]
[嘟嘟声]
- [laughing]
- [笑]
[upbeat music]
[欢快的音乐]
♪ ♪